
[
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is a way to manipulate immune response. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Using a live vaccine is better than using a killed vaccine because it involves MHC II antigen presentation.",
      "B": "The variolation introduced by the Chinese in 16th century was, in particular, the same as the vaccination introduced by Edward Jenner.",
      "C": "The process of making a traditionally labor-intensive attenuated live vaccine using non-human cell line can be sped up using recombinant DNA technology.",
      "D": "Although a peptide-based vaccine is safer, it is less effective than a live vaccine."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "辨識自我、非我的能力為後天免疫系統的特性，是免疫細胞後天不斷比較自身細胞抗原來學習，故此能力不是由遺傳而得。 [出自考古第1題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Brunet's postulate on the clonal selection has laid the foundations of adaptive immunity. Based on clonal selection, which is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "A progenitor cell can generate a large number of lymphocytes, each with different specificity, including self-reactive and non-self reactive.",
      "B": "Once mature, a specific lymphocyte can be activated, proliferate, differentiate, and form a clone of effector cells.",
      "C": "If a transplantation (different strain) occurs during fetus stage, it won't be rejected.",
      "D": "The ability to differentiate self and non-self is hereditary."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D)辨識自我、非我的能力為後天免疫系統的特性，是免疫細胞後天不斷比較自身細胞抗原來學習，故此能力不是由遺傳而得。 [出自考古第2題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tyrosine signaling is very important in immunology. Which of the statements about tyrosine phosphorylation is incorrect?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Tyrosine on the receptor is phosphorylated for initiation.",
      "B": "Scaffold protein is phosphorylated to recruit downstream molecules.",
      "C": "When the phosphate is removed, the signal will be terminated.",
      "D": "Non-tyrosine kinase receptors use intracellular kinase domain to phosphorylate it downstream molecules."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D)Non-tyrosine kinase receptors 的胞內區域並沒有 Kinase 功能區，而是藉由吸引 Kinase 與受體的胞內區域進行非共價結合。(見共筆 Vol.1 P.50) [出自考古第3題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "AMPs (antimicrobial peptides) are involved in innate immunity. Which of the following description concerning AMPs is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "AMPs can be secreted by the epithelium cells of lung and guts.",
      "B": "Cathelithidin, defensins, lysozymes are all AMPs.",
      "C": "AMPs are amphipathic and bear a hydrophilic end and a hydrophobic end.",
      "D": "AMPs are only activated when being cleaved by the protease."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "(B)AMPs 包含了 Cathelithidin 以及 Defensin。Lysozyme 為上皮組織所製造，用於分解細菌的細胞壁，隨後再由 AMPs 使細胞膜穿孔。 [出自考古第4題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Upon activation, ITAM 會 Recruit kinase, ITIM 會 Recruit phosphatase",
      "B": "TCR有10個ITAM,BCR有2個ITAM",
      "C": "(選項遺失)",
      "D": "If a new synthetic TCR has an ITIM in its intracellular domain, the activation of the TCR will down-regulate the signaling pathway."
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "{09勘誤內容:答案欄給C,詳解給B,因 ITAM 數量眾說紛紜且C選項佚失,故不確定答案。(筆者認為 TCR 和 BCR 在細胞內區域無 ITAM ) } [出自考古第5題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "immunity suppression drugs, which is not correct?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Cyclosporin 用 Ca2+ 使 NFkB 失去作用",
      "B": "類固醇進核使細胞介素無法轉錄",
      "C": "Anti IL-6 antigen 使免疫細胞不分泌細胞介素",
      "D": "Anti-TNF α 使之失去作用"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A) Cyclosporine 是從真菌 Tolypocladium inflatum Gams 分離出的成分,可與T cell 內的 cyclophilin receptor 結合,而抑制 calcineurin phosphatase 的活性,進而抑制 NF-AT (nuclear factor of activated T lymphocytes)去磷酸化 (dephosphorylation)。\n簡單來說就是:Cyclosporine 可以抑制T細胞的增殖。 [出自考古第6題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "(原題目為英文)關於MZB(marginal zone B-cell)哪項正確?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Fetus 就有。",
      "B": "對 Carbohydrate antigen 不反應。",
      "C": "主要分泌 IgG。",
      "D": "Replaced from bone marrow.",
      "E": "Primary location is spleen."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "熟記單元 7 p.34 表格。 [出自考古第1題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following immunodeficiency has no B, T and NK cells in both mice and human?",
    "options": {
      "A": "RAG1 deficiency.",
      "B": "RAG2 deficiency.",
      "C": "IL-7 receptor deficiency.",
      "D": "Artemis deficiency.",
      "E": "ADA deficiency."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "(E) T⁻B⁻NK⁻,ADA 參與嘌呤合成的補救途徑(salvage pathway),影響幹細胞分裂、分化。 [出自考古第2題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT involved in positive selection?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CD4 co-receptor.",
      "B": "Macrophages in thymus.",
      "C": "MHC class II on thymic epithelial cells.",
      "D": "Peptides on MHC class I.",
      "E": "Thymic cortical epithelial cells."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "(B) 巨噬細胞參與的是負選擇。 [出自考古第3題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the receptor of CCL21?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CCR1.",
      "B": "CCR7.",
      "C": "CXCR4.",
      "D": "CXCR5.",
      "E": "CXCR1."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "(B) T細胞上的 CCR7 是 HEV 上皮細胞所分泌的 CCL21 的受體。 [出自考古第4題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following molecule is NOT involved in T lymphocyte migration?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CD-4.",
      "B": "GlyCAM-1.",
      "C": "L-selectin.",
      "D": "LFA-1.",
      "E": "ICAM-1."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "(D)(E) 參與黏附。 [出自考古第5題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "STAT-6 會使 T細胞分化成甚麼細胞?",
    "options": {
      "A": "T$_{H}$1.",
      "B": "T$_{H}$2.",
      "C": "T$_{H}$17.",
      "D": "T$_{FH}$.",
      "E": "T$_{reg}$."
    },
    "answer": "B",
    "explanation": "熟記單元 10 p.37 上方表格。 [出自考古第6題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "T$_{H}$1 主要是針對甚麼細胞活化?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Macrophage.",
      "B": "Neutrophil."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "熟記單元 10 p.37下方表格。 [出自考古第7題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "活化的CD8T細胞不會釋放下列何種物質?",
    "options": {
      "A": "IL-4.",
      "B": "Perforin.",
      "C": "IFN-γ.",
      "D": "TNF-α.",
      "E": "Granzymes."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A) CD8 T細胞不會釋放 IL-4。 [出自考古第8題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "The one which reacts in BCR recombination?",
    "options": {
      "A": "TdT.",
      "B": "DNA polymerase.",
      "C": "DNA exonuclease.",
      "D": "AID.",
      "E": "V(D)J recombinase."
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "(E) V(D)J recombinase: a multiprotein complex containing RAG-1 and RAG-2, as well as other proteins involved in cellular DNA repair。\n【出處:Janeway 9th edition CH12 P.853】 [出自考古第1題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "MHC genes are highly polymorphic. During TCR and MHC recognition, TCR binds to the peptide fit in the groove. Which one else does TCR bond?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Anchor peptide.",
      "B": "(選項遺失)",
      "C": "the β2 microglobulin.",
      "D": "the α helix of MHC."
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "MHC 分子的 Peptide-binding cleft由 α helix 組成,而TCR的可變區(V)便會與其結合。 [出自考古第2題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "MHC class 2 is composed of ______ chain, and it presents antigen to ______ T cells",
    "options": {
      "A": "α and β; CD4.",
      "B": "α and β2 microglobulin; CD4.",
      "C": "α and β; CD8.",
      "D": "α and β2 microglobulin; CD8.",
      "E": "α and β; γ:δ."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "MHCI由α、β2 microglobulin 構成,會與CD8 結合;MHC II由α、β構成,會與 CD4 結合。 [出自考古第3題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Matching: pick up the right answer from the below list. (single choice, 1 point each)\n(1) Anaphylaxis\n(2) Contact dermatitis\n(3) Stevens-Johnson syndrome\n(4) Serum sickness",
    "options": {
      "A": "Type I hypersensitivity",
      "B": "Type II hypersensitivity",
      "C": "Type III hypersensitivity",
      "D": "Both Type II and Type III hypersensitivity",
      "E": "Type I, II and III hypersensitivity",
      "F": "Type IV hypersensitivity",
      "G": "All of the Type I, II, III and IV hypersensitivity",
      "H": "None of any type of hypersensitivity"
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "第一型過敏反應:食物過敏、氣喘、Rhinoconjunctivitis、急性蕁麻疹(acute urticaria)、過敏性休克(anaphylaxis) [出自考古第1-(1)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Matching: pick up the right answer from the below list. (single choice, 1 point each)\n(1) Anaphylaxis\n(2) Contact dermatitis\n(3) Stevens-Johnson syndrome\n(4) Serum sickness",
    "options": {
      "A": "Type I hypersensitivity",
      "B": "Type II hypersensitivity",
      "C": "Type III hypersensitivity",
      "D": "Both Type II and Type III hypersensitivity",
      "E": "Type I, II and III hypersensitivity",
      "F": "Type IV hypersensitivity",
      "G": "All of the Type I, II, III and IV hypersensitivity",
      "H": "None of any type of hypersensitivity"
    },
    "answer": "F",
    "explanation": "第四型過敏反應:皮膚結核菌素測驗(tuberculin skin test)、接觸性皮膚炎(allergic contact dermatitis),麩質敏感性腸疾(gluten-sensitive enteropathy)、Stevens-Johnson syndrome [出自考古第1-(2)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Matching: pick up the right answer from the below list. (single choice, 1 point each)\n(1) Anaphylaxis\n(2) Contact dermatitis\n(3) Stevens-Johnson syndrome\n(4) Serum sickness",
    "options": {
      "A": "Type I hypersensitivity",
      "B": "Type II hypersensitivity",
      "C": "Type III hypersensitivity",
      "D": "Both Type II and Type III hypersensitivity",
      "E": "Type I, II and III hypersensitivity",
      "F": "Type IV hypersensitivity",
      "G": "All of the Type I, II, III and IV hypersensitivity",
      "H": "None of any type of hypersensitivity"
    },
    "answer": "F",
    "explanation": "第四型過敏反應:皮膚結核菌素測驗(tuberculin skin test)、接觸性皮膚炎(allergic contact dermatitis),麩質敏感性腸疾(gluten-sensitive enteropathy)、Stevens-Johnson syndrome [出自考古第1-(3)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Matching: pick up the right answer from the below list. (single choice, 1 point each)\n(1) Anaphylaxis\n(2) Contact dermatitis\n(3) Stevens-Johnson syndrome\n(4) Serum sickness",
    "options": {
      "A": "Type I hypersensitivity",
      "B": "Type II hypersensitivity",
      "C": "Type III hypersensitivity",
      "D": "Both Type II and Type III hypersensitivity",
      "E": "Type I, II and III hypersensitivity",
      "F": "Type IV hypersensitivity",
      "G": "All of the Type I, II, III and IV hypersensitivity",
      "H": "None of any type of hypersensitivity"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "第三型過敏反應:血清病(serum sickness) [出自考古第1-(4)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "For each of the following select the most appropriate characteristic listed below.\n(a) Experimental allergic encephalomyelitis (EAE)",
    "options": {
      "1": "Auto-antibodies to acetylcholine receptor",
      "2": "T$_{H}$1-cell reaction to antigens",
      "3": "Autoimmunity due to lack of regulatory T cell activity",
      "4": "An autoimmune disease due to T cell response to neurons",
      "5": "Induced by injection of myelin basic protein plus complete Freund's adjuvant",
      "6": "Auto-antibodies to basement membrane",
      "7": "Auto-antibodies to DNA and DNA-associated protein",
      "8": "Induced by injection of acetylcholine receptors",
      "9": "T-cell response to pancreatic β cell",
      "10": "Anti-bacteria cell wall antibody cross-react with cardiac tissue",
      "11": "Associated with HLA-B27",
      "12": "Cytotoxic T cell response to thyroid tissues",
      "13": "Baruj Benacerraf",
      "14": "G. Snell",
      "15": "P. Doherty",
      "16": "D. Baltimore",
      "17": "S. Tonegawa"
    },
    "answer": "5",
    "explanation": "5. 實驗性過敏腦脊髓炎(EAE,experimental allergic encephalomyelitis) [出自考古第2-(a)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "For each of the following select the most appropriate characteristic listed below.\n(b) Inflammatory bowel disease",
    "options": {
      "1": "Auto-antibodies to acetylcholine receptor",
      "2": "T$_{H}$1-cell reaction to antigens",
      "3": "Autoimmunity due to lack of regulatory T cell activity",
      "4": "An autoimmune disease due to T cell response to neurons",
      "5": "Induced by injection of myelin basic protein plus complete Freund's adjuvant",
      "6": "Auto-antibodies to basement membrane",
      "7": "Auto-antibodies to DNA and DNA-associated protein",
      "8": "Induced by injection of acetylcholine receptors",
      "9": "T-cell response to pancreatic β cell",
      "10": "Anti-bacteria cell wall antibody cross-react with cardiac tissue",
      "11": "Associated with HLA-B27",
      "12": "Cytotoxic T cell response to thyroid tissues",
      "13": "Baruj Benacerraf",
      "14": "G. Snell",
      "15": "P. Doherty",
      "16": "D. Baltimore",
      "17": "S. Tonegawa"
    },
    "answer": "3",
    "explanation": "3. 發炎性腸道疾病(IBD,inflammatory bowel disease):異種移植(xenograft)會出現。 [出自考古第2-(b)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "For each of the following select the most appropriate characteristic listed below.\n(c) Myasthenia gravis",
    "options": {
      "1": "Auto-antibodies to acetylcholine receptor",
      "2": "T$_{H}$1-cell reaction to antigens",
      "3": "Autoimmunity due to lack of regulatory T cell activity",
      "4": "An autoimmune disease due to T cell response to neurons",
      "5": "Induced by injection of myelin basic protein plus complete Freund's adjuvant",
      "6": "Auto-antibodies to basement membrane",
      "7": "Auto-antibodies to DNA and DNA-associated protein",
      "8": "Induced by injection of acetylcholine receptors",
      "9": "T-cell response to pancreatic β cell",
      "10": "Anti-bacteria cell wall antibody cross-react with cardiac tissue",
      "11": "Associated with HLA-B27",
      "12": "Cytotoxic T cell response to thyroid tissues",
      "13": "Baruj Benacerraf",
      "14": "G. Snell",
      "15": "P. Doherty",
      "16": "D. Baltimore",
      "17": "S. Tonegawa"
    },
    "answer": "1",
    "explanation": "1. 重症肌無力(myasthenia gravis):抗體異常地結合阻礙菸鹼型乙醯膽鹼受體(nicotinic acetylcholine receptor)。 [出自考古第2-(c)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "For each of the following select the most appropriate characteristic listed below.\n(d) The scientist who discovered MHC restriction and won Nobel prize",
    "options": {
      "1": "Auto-antibodies to acetylcholine receptor",
      "2": "T$_{H}$1-cell reaction to antigens",
      "3": "Autoimmunity due to lack of regulatory T cell activity",
      "4": "An autoimmune disease due to T cell response to neurons",
      "5": "Induced by injection of myelin basic protein plus complete Freund's adjuvant",
      "6": "Auto-antibodies to basement membrane",
      "7": "Auto-antibodies to DNA and DNA-associated protein",
      "8": "Induced by injection of acetylcholine receptors",
      "9": "T-cell response to pancreatic β cell",
      "10": "Anti-bacteria cell wall antibody cross-react with cardiac tissue",
      "11": "Associated with HLA-B27",
      "12": "Cytotoxic T cell response to thyroid tissues",
      "13": "Baruj Benacerraf",
      "14": "G. Snell",
      "15": "P. Doherty",
      "16": "D. Baltimore",
      "17": "S. Tonegawa"
    },
    "answer": "15",
    "explanation": "15. MHC restriction [出自考古第2-(d)題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following molecules is recently found to be associated with severe drug hypersensitivity reaction, Stevens-Johnson syndrome, to anti-seizure drug carbamazepine?",
    "options": {
      "A": "CTLA4",
      "B": "RORYT",
      "C": "HLA",
      "D": "Foxp-3",
      "E": "Interferon gamma (IFN-γ)"
    },
    "answer": "C",
    "explanation": "[出自考古第4題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "You cross two inbred strain mice A and B to have F1, then you further cross these F1 to generate F2. If you transplant the skin graft from parent A to one of the F2 mice, what will be the chance the skin graft is rejected?",
    "options": {
      "A": "100%",
      "B": "75%",
      "C": "50%",
      "D": "25%",
      "E": "0%"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "F2 基因型:AA : AB : BB = 1 : 2 : 1\n將AA 移植到F2時,只要子代有A的等位基因(allele)就不會排斥,由於F2 中只有BB 不具有A,故排斥率為 25%。 [出自考古第5題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about “X-linked hyper IgM syndrome” is incorrect?",
    "options": {
      "A": "This is immunodeficiency affects both B cell and T cell",
      "B": "There is a defect in CD40L, a critical molecule expressed on T cells",
      "C": "Because CD40-CD40L is important for B cell class-switching, IgM is increased and IgG is decreased",
      "D": "Patients are usually asymptomatic and only develops opportunistic infection",
      "E": "Besides extracellular bacteria, protection against intracellular pathogen is also impaired"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D)仍有症狀產生,只是較不嚴重。 [出自考古第1題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about influenza virus is incorrect?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Severe epidemic is caused by antigenic drift.",
      "B": "Influenza is an RNA virus.",
      "C": "Low fidelity of RNA polymerase cause mutations in antigenic drift.",
      "D": "Influenza does not integrate its genome into host DNA.",
      "E": "Influenza virus is smaller than other larger DNA viruses."
    },
    "answer": "A",
    "explanation": "(A)應是 Antigenic shift 而非 Antigenic drift,代表多株病毒混和,新的病毒表面的抗原具有原本幾種病毒表面抗原的特徵。Antigenic drift 是指,病毒表面抗原的基因發生突變,使病毒表面的抗原出現變異,人體原本的抗體和新抗原結合能力改變,但人體內原本的抗體仍存在著一些 Cross protection 的效果,故只造成流感的小流行。 [出自考古第2題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following immunodeficiency has no B, T and NK cells in both mice and human?",
    "options": {
      "A": "RAG1 deficiency",
      "B": "RAG2 deficiency",
      "C": "IL-7 receptor deficiency",
      "D": "Artemis deficiency",
      "E": "ADA deficiency (B98 MT II, B92 MT III )"
    },
    "answer": "E",
    "explanation": "(E) ADA 酵素失去功能會讓 CLP 無法分化成T和B細胞和NK細胞,造成 SCID。 [出自考古第3題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statement about adoptive T cell therapy for cancer is incorrect?",
    "options": {
      "A": "Endogenous T cells specific for tumor antigen can be expanded for transfusion in patients",
      "B": "TCR gene transfer can produce different T cells with the same antigen specificity",
      "C": "CAR-T cell therapy has been successful in treating hematological cancers",
      "D": "CAR-T cells are not genetically modified T cells",
      "E": "Quantity of infused T cells is as important as quantity of cell products"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D) CAR-T技術是從病人身上抽出T細胞,利用反轉錄病毒對其進行遺傳修飾,讓T細胞表現嵌合抗原受體(CAR,chimeric antigen receptor),使其能辨識腫瘤的細胞。 [出自考古第4題]"
  },
  {
    "question": "About immune checkpoint therapy, which one is incorrect?",
    "options": {
      "A": "It works by activating exhausted tumor-infiltrating T cells",
      "B": "Tumors PD-L1 expression can be used to predict responsiveness toward therapy",
      "C": "Tumors with high mutation burden are usually more immunogenic thus more responsive",
      "D": "Tumors cells express not only PD-1 but other inhibitory molecules",
      "E": "Combination treatment of adoptive T cell therapy with checkpoint blockade is synergistic"
    },
    "answer": "D",
    "explanation": "(D)腫瘤細胞是表現 PD-L1;PD-1 是 T細胞表現的。 [出自考古第5題]"
  }
]
